{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In the 1940s, this man appeared on posters advocating that war workers use suggestion boxes, and he also was shown advocating the purchase of bonds alongside Lady Columbia, whom he largely replaced. This man, whose common image is based on Horatio Kitchener, says \"I want you!\" in a recruiting poster. For 10 points, name this personification of the United States.",
      "answer": "Uncle Sam"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the 2000s, this institution underwent a controversy when its president, former Treasury Secretary Lawrence Summers, was accused of making disparaging remarks about women's intelligence. This institution, whose early presidents included Increase Mather, is now led by Civil War historian Drew Gilpin Faust. For 10 points, name this university in Massachussetts.",
      "answer": "Harvard University"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man focused on social productive forces, his nation’s advanced culture, and the interests of the majority as his “Three Represents” doctrine. This man succeeded Zhao Ziyang as General Secretary after the former’s dismissal by Deng Xiaoping after the Tiananmen Massacre. For 10 points, name this leader of the Chinese Communist Party during the 1990s.",
      "answer": "Jiang Zemin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization was led in the mid-twentieth century by Walter White, who oversaw publication of its journal, The Crisis. This organization was founded out of the Niagara Movement following the 1908 Springfield riot by people such as W.E.B. Du Bois. For 10 points, name this black civil rights group, which successfully argued the Brown v. Board case.",
      "answer": "NAACP"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's little-used middle names are \"Plantagenet\" and \"Schicklgruber.\"His Social Security number is 000-00-0002, and he never forgave his mother for her affair with President Taft. He looted paintings from a Nazi stronghold as part of the Flying Hellfish. For 10 points, name this employer of Waylon Smithers and very old proprietor of the Springfield Nuclear Power Plant.",
      "answer": "Charles Montgomery Burns"
    },
    {
      "question": "Much of the Roman conquest of this island was carried out under Gnaeus Julius Agricola. The mercenaries Hengist and Horsa were invited to this island by Vortigern. The Iceni were led in an uprising by their queen Boudicca on this island. Julius Caesar visited this island twice during his conquest of Gaul. For 10 points, which island experienced a fifth-century invasion by Jutes, Saxons, and Angles?",
      "answer": "Great Britain"
    },
    {
      "question": "A member of this family moved to Arkansas to become that state's first post-Reconstruction Republican governor. Another member of this family founded the University of Chicago, and another was criticized for his flippant handling of the Attica prison riot. For 10 points, what family included Standard Oil baron John and New York governor Nelson?",
      "answer": "Rockefeller"
    },
    {
      "question": "This dynasty accepted the surrender of the Kotte kingdom. The Kraak trade, begun late in this dynasty's rule, began exporting blue and white porcelain to Europe en masse. This dynasty scuttled its \"Treasure Fleet\" after sending out the expeditions of Zheng He. This dynasty fell to Manchu invaders in 1644. For 10 points, name this Chinese dynasty between the Yuan and Qing.",
      "answer": "Ming dynasty"
    },
    {
      "question": "A major leader of this party defected to become the Republican governor of Massachussetts; that was Nathaniel Banks. This party often rioted against Catholics, including burning down a church in Maine, and it nominated Millard Fillmore for President in 1856. For 10 points, name this anti-immigrant party which briefly arose prior to the Civil War.",
      "answer": "Know-Nothing Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "Albania and Kosovo are the only European countries where a majority practices this religion. The Danish Jyllands-Posten caused an uproar in 2005 when it printed cartoons critical of an important figure in this religion. A 2009 Swiss referendum banned the construction of its minarets. For 10 points, name this religion whose followers read the Koran.",
      "answer": "Islam NHBB B 2014-2015"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This organization was targeted in November 2014 by the hashtag \"Things That Are Not Mosques\" after it erroneously identified Westminster Cathedral as a mosque. This organization, which is represented in polling maps by the color purple, is led by former metal commodities trader Nigel Farage. For 10 points, name this right-wing party that is surging in the U.K.",
        "answer": "UKIP"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "UKIP is currently polling as the third most popular party in the U.K., displacing what coalition partner of the Conservatives led by Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg?",
        "answer": "Liberal Democrats"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man first calculated the angular radius of a rainbow using Snell's Law. This man, who believed that the pineal gland joined the body to the soul, first used two axes to display four quadrants, creating his namesake coordinate plane. For 10 points, name this mathematician and philosopher who stated \"cogito ergo sum\" or \"I think therefore I am.\"",
        "answer": "Rene Descartes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Descartes also discovered what technique for determing the possible numbers of a function's roots by examining the pattern of positive and negative terms?",
        "answer": "Descartes's rule of signs"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In ths play, Fluellen ironically notes that Alexander the Great killed his best friend Cleitus (CLEE-tuss) the Black. This play's prologue asks for a \"muse of fire,\" and the St. Crispin's Day speech from this play praises \"We happy few, we band of brothers.\" For 10 points, name this Shakespeare play which depicts the title king's victory at the Battle of Agincourt (AA-jin-core).",
        "answer": "Henry V"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In what other Shakespeare history play does the \"sun of York\" lament \"my kingdom for a horse\" while losing the Battle of Bosworth Field?",
        "answer": "Richard III"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The oldest event of this type in the U.S. takes place in Mobile, Alabama and is organized by groups such as the Mystic Stripers. Another of these events is organized by \"krewes\" (crews) who travel down St. Charles Avenue and Canal Street to avoid obstructions to floats in the French Quarter. For 10 points, name this day on which pre-Lent Carnival parades take place.",
        "answer": "Mardi Gras parades"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The New Orleans Mardi Gras flag contains gold, green, and what other color, whose \"Tyrian\" (TEER-ee-un) form was used to dye the togas of important Romans?",
        "answer": "purple"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A well-regarded American example of this genre is Douglas Moore's The Ballad of Baby Doe. Samuel Barber worked in this genre to create Vanessa, for which another composer wrote the lost The Guest of Honor. For 10 points, name this musical genre of Scott Joplin's Treemonisha, John Adams's Nixon in China, and George Gershwin's Porgy and Bess",
        "answer": "American operas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A recent John Adams opera at the met about the death of which victim of the Achille Lauro highjacking, met with controversy over accusations of anti-Semitism?",
        "answer": [
          "Leon Klinghoffer",
          "The Death of Klinghoffer"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In response to Joseph Stalin's order to oppose this bill, Pete Seeger released the song \"Plow Under.\" This bill, which expanded on the \"destroyers for bases\" program, was likened to giving a hose to a neighbor whose house is burning down. For 10 points, name this bill that instituted a nine-month period of supplying the Allies before the U.S. entered World War II.",
        "answer": "Lend-Lease Act"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What German operation invading the Soviet Union caused Communists to switch their support to the pro-war side?",
        "answer": "Operation Barbarossa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Popular names for this event include an Gorta Mor and the Black 47. The simultaneous export of grain and meat products have labelled some historians to claim it was a genocide. This event was caused by an organism called phytophthora infestans or late blight. For 10 points, name this late 1840s event in which widespread crop failures caused mass starvation on a British island.",
        "answer": "Irish Potato Famine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Irish-English relations were further strained by what English land agent for Lord Erne who lends his name to a popular protest measure?",
        "answer": "Charles Cuunningham Boycott"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman hosted the reality show Mr. Personality and wrote the 2014 article \"Shame and Survival,\" which continues her criticism of her depiction in the book My Life. This employee of the Office of Legislative Affairs was secretly taped by Linda Tripp, who referred her to Kenneth Starr. For 10 points, identify this namesake of a sex scandal in the Clinton administration.",
        "answer": "Monica Lewinsky"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lewinsky scandal was revealed four years after what Arkansas civil servant sued President Clinton for a 1991 sexual harassment incident?",
        "answer": "Paula Jones NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "POSTWAR EUROPEAN QUOTES",
      "prompt": "Who said...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“An Iron Curtain has descended across the Continent” in a speech delivered in Fulton, Missouri?",
          "answer": "Winston Churchill"
        },
        {
          "question": "“The lady's not for turning” when refusing to slow her liberalization of Britain's economy?",
          "answer": "Margaret Thatcher"
        },
        {
          "question": "“We will bury you” to Western ambassadors?",
          "answer": "Nikita Khrushchev"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Soviet Union could not “improve thing without changing anything” in a party speech introducing his perestroika policy?",
          "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Gaudet Mater Ecclesia” in his declaration opening Vatican II?",
          "answer": "John XXIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Non” in response to Great Britain joining the European Economic Community?",
          "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
        },
        {
          "question": "“This is our breakthrough” after his West Germany agreed to enter the European Coal and Steel Community?",
          "answer": "Konrad Adenauer"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Most of our people have never had it so good” while running for prime minister?",
          "answer": "Harold Macmillian"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE FIRST GULF WAR",
      "prompt": "Who or what was…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The dictator of Iraq during the First Gulf War?",
          "answer": "Saddam Hussain"
        },
        {
          "question": "The nation accused of “slant drilling” that was invaded by Iraqi forces in 1990?",
          "answer": "Kuwait"
        },
        {
          "question": "The codename given to the American-led offensive into Iraq?",
          "answer": "Operation Desert Storm"
        },
        {
          "question": "The leader of American forces in the conflict, given the nickname “Stormin’”?",
          "answer": "Norman Schwarzkopf, Jr"
        },
        {
          "question": "The pyrophoric, armor-piercing radioactive material used in coalition weapons thought to contribute to Gulf War syndrome?",
          "answer": "depleted uranium"
        },
        {
          "question": "The elite Iraqi military force led by General al-Rawi that included the Hammurabi armored division?",
          "answer": "Republican Guard"
        },
        {
          "question": "The road from Kuwait City to Basra used by retreating Iraqi columns that was bombed repeatedly by Coalition forces?",
          "answer": "Highway of Death"
        },
        {
          "question": "Strategy, named for a boxing move, in which flanking divisions approached Iraqi forces from the west while others ran straight through the Kuwaiti border?",
          "answer": "Left Hook"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "GAMAL ABDEL NASSER",
      "prompt": "Who or what was…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The nation ruled by Nasser until his death from a heart attack?",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military officer who succeeded Nasser to the Presidency?",
          "answer": "Anwar Sadat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Artificial waterway nationalized by Nasser, leading to British and French intervention?",
          "answer": "Suez canal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dam funded by the USSR that eventually created Lake Nasser",
          "answer": "Aswan Dam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military clique of high ranking members which Nasser was a member?",
          "answer": "Free Officers Movement"
        },
        {
          "question": "Short-lived political Union between Syria and Nasser’s nation?",
          "answer": "United Arab Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nation on the Arabian Peninsula whose Northern half Nasser invaded in its 1962-70 civil war?",
          "answer": "North Yemen"
        },
        {
          "question": "The King whom Nasser overthrew to begin his reign?",
          "answer": "King Farouk NHBB B 2014-2015"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man refuted the Patriarcha of Robert Filmer in a close reading whose sequel introduced the concept of \"mixing labor\" with land to create property. This man's (20 pts)",
        "Some Thoughts Concerning Education expanded on his concept of the mind as a (10 pts)",
        "\"tabula rasa\" or \"blank state.\" He wrote slavery into the constitution of the Carolinas. For 10 points, name this author of Two Treatises on Government which advocated a positive, non-Hobbesian notion of the social contract."
      ],
      "answer": "John Locke"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Apart from Morehead State, one team from this state has won the Ohio Valley Conference 23 times. The most successful team from this state has the most wins in college basketball history. Two teams in this state met in the Final Four of the (20 pts)",
        "2012 NCAA Tournament, and the winning team was led by players such as Michael (10 pts)",
        "Kidd-Gilchrist and Anthony Davis. For 10 points, name this state whose two most successful college basketball teams are led by John Calipari and Rick Pitino, who has coached at Louisville since 2001."
      ],
      "answer": "Kentucky"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1987, this agent was found in the preserved body of Robert Rayford, who had died in St. Louis in 1969. In 1983, this agent was independently discovered by Robert Gallo and (20 pts)",
        "Luc Montagnier, who were investigating a disease then known as GRIDS. Gaetan Dugas is sometimes called the (10 pts)",
        "\"Patient Zero\" of this virus in the United States. For 10 points, name this retrovirus discovered in 1983 to be the cause of AIDS."
      ],
      "answer": "HIV"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While this artist was staying with Mabel Dodge Luhan, a visit to the D.H. Lawrence Ranch inspired her oil painting The Lawrence Tree. After 1946, this artist incorporated her (20 pts)",
        "Abiquiu home into her paintings. In 1916, her future husband Alfred (10 pts)",
        "Stieglitz began displaying her paintings in his 291 gallery. For 10 points, name this woman whose depictions of the American Southwest are located in her namesake museum in Santa Fe."
      ],
      "answer": "Georgia O’Keeffe"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This family abolished the post of Gonfaloniere of Justice. An early member of this family helped suppress the revolt of wool-carders called Ciompi. Two members of this family were attacked at High Mass during the (20 pts)",
        "Pazzi Conspiracy. A member of this family, Piero the Unfortunate, lost power to a friar who held the (10 pts)",
        "\"bonfire of the vanities,\" Domenico Savonarola. For 10 points, name this family headed by Cosimo and Lorenzo, which ruled Florence."
      ],
      "answer": "House of Medici"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A society along this non-European river made seals showing a seated horned god surrounded by animals and a bitumen-lined Great Bath. Sites along this river include the early port of (20 pts)",
        "Lothal, a site whose name means \"mound of death,\" Mohenjo-Daro, and the mudbrick city of (10 pts)",
        "Harappa, built around 2000 BCE before Aryan peoples arrived in the area. Alexander the Great turned back shortly after crossing, for 10 points, what river that flows south through Pakistan?"
      ],
      "answer": "Indus river"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) David Harris's Omega organization advocated this activity. A Phil Ochs song about doing this listed flat feet and a ruptured spleen as ways to accomplish it. Nearly all people who did this were pardoned by Jimmy Carter, though accusations of doing it have since haunted (20 pts)",
        "Bill Clinton, George W. Bush, and Dick Cheney. Many people who did this temporarily (10 pts)",
        "fled to Canada. For 10 points, what was this activity which people who did not wish to fight in Vietnam performed?"
      ],
      "answer": "Vietnam \"draft dodging\""
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) King Charles XII of Sweden planned to adopt this system over a period of forty years from 1700 to 1740, but gave up in 1711. The adoption of this system in England in 1750 apocryphally caused rioters to chant “Give us our (20 pts)",
        "eleven days.” The major change of this system over its predecessor is its treatment of (10 pts)",
        "years divisible by 400. For 10 points, name this calendar system which replaced the Julian Calendar and which is named for the Pope who introduced it in 1582."
      ],
      "answer": "Gregorian calendar NHBB B 2014-2015"
    }
  ]
}